STEFANO CASTRO TOGNINI

♀ Oak Ridge National Laboratory

@ togninis@ornl.gov

4 +1 (865) 341 0453

stognini

in stognini

I have a **Ph.D.** in **Physics**, focused in High Energy Physics. Currently a **Research Associate at Oak Ridge National Laboratory** working on Monte Carlo development for the DOE Exascale Computing Project. In the past I was a **collaborator at Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory** (Fermilab), working as a Master's, and later on Ph.D. candidate, in two experiments known as MINOS and NO ν A. These are long-term multi-million dollar endeavors built to understand the nature of neutrinos and answer fundamental questions related to astrophysics, dark matter, and more. Each experiment is a worldwide effort encompassing up to 300 scientists. My **7+ years of experience** working with diversified teams produced many **published data analyses**, all developed using **C++**, **Python**, **ROOT**, **shell scripting**, **massive parallel computing**, **and Monte Carlo simulations**. Software development is managed using **version control (GIT/SVN)**, allied with automated code referencing (**Doxygen**). Production of **technical documentation** is routinely done. Finally, I have experience with **teaching** at the undergraduate level, **mentoring** graduate students, presenting findings at international conferences, as well as participating in **science outreach** events.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Associate

Oak Ridge National Laboratory HPC Methods for Nuclear Applications Group Nuclear Energy and Fuel Cycle Division

2019 - Present

Oak Ridge (TN)

COLLABORATIONS

Celeritas Project

github.com/celeritas-project

2020 - Present

♀ ORNL

- **1.** Core member of the Celeritas development team.
- 2. Implemented electromagnetic physics processes.
- 3. Implemented import tools to load Geant4 data into Celeritas.
- 4. Developed physics validations tools
- Developed an event display to visualize detector geometry and particle information.

URL Muon Detector Project

2020 - Present

♀ ORNL

1. Core team member involved with all stages of the project: Detector design, simulation, commissioning, deployment, and analysis.

NO ν **A** Experiment

novaexperiment.fnal.gov

2013 - 2018

- **♀** Fermilab / ANL / UFG
- 1. Leading author of a published data analysis: PRD 99 122004
- 2. Integrated a Monte Carlo package with the Fermilab computing framework that is being used by two other experiments at Fermilab and CERN.
- 3. Commissioned/maintained a Remote Operation Center (ROC) at UFG.
- **4.** Hardware work that consisted in testing the quality of Avalanche Photo Diodes before being installed in the NO ν A detector.

MINOS Experiment

www-numi.fnal.gov

2011 - 2018

- 1. Worked in 2 published data analyses: PRD 91 112006 / PRD 93 052017.
- 2. Wrote documentation for commissioning and certifying ROCs.
- 3. Installed and maintained the MINOS Main Operation Center at Fermilab.
- 4. Built, documented, and maintained a MINOS ROC at UFG.

SCIENTIFIC PUBLICATIONS

SOFT SKILLS

Teaching (3 yrs) Mentoring (4 yrs)

Scientific outreach Public speaking

Portuguese (native) English Italian French



HARD SKILLS

Technical skills

Data structuring | Parallel computing

Data querying Data analysis

Monte Carlo simulation

Data visualization

Programming & scripting languages

C/C++ Python SQL Shell LATEX

Frameworks, libraries, databases, & tools

Fermilab ART Framework ROOT

Geant4 CORSIKA Redmine

Doxygen GIT PBS TORQUE

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Physics - High Energy Physics

Federal University of Goias, Brazil

Funding: CAPES, CNPq, Argonne

2012 - 2018

DOE OSTI www.osti.gov/biblio/1468447 iNSPIRE HEP inspirehep.net/record/1692030

M.Sc. in Physics - High Energy Physics

Federal University of Goias, Brazil

Funding: CAPES, Fermilab

2010 - 2012

B.Sc. in Physics

Federal University of Goias, Brazil

2005 - 2010